<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Discourses upon the modern affairs of Europe tending to prove that the illustrious French monarchy may be reduced to terms of greater moderation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1630</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24999</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08713091</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08713091</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41638</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36118)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41638)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1256:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Discourses upon the modern affairs of Europe tending to prove that the illustrious French monarchy may be reduced to terms of greater moderation.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated "Hague. May 24, 80."--p. 22.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Europe --  Politics and government --  1648-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41638:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41638:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DISCOURSES UPON THE <hi>Modern Affairs</hi> OF EUROPE, Tending to prove, that the Illuſtrious FRENCH MONARCHY may be reduced to <hi>terms</hi> of greater moderation.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Dì Dendri, dì ſénno, e dì Féde,</l>
               <l>C'n'è mánco ché non Créde.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>There is commonly leſs Money, leſs Wiſdom, and leſs good Faith than men do account upon.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Verulam.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Et digiti pedum, partim ſunt e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ferro, &amp; partim ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quia exparte regnum futurum eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urum, &amp; ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arte foturum eſt fragile,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Dan. 2.42.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:41638:2"/>
            <head>The PUBLISHER to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Author</hi> of theſe Diſcourſes I know not. But the ſame coming to my hands, beyond any expectation of mine, I thought I was bound to give the Publick (whoſe mark is upon them) credi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſame. And becauſe it is one eſſential property of a good Merchant to pay well, I alſo thought my ſelf obliged to render the effects of ſo good a <hi>hit,</hi> into the common Bank, where they are due. It is true, there are ſome things in them, which ſeem not ſo fit for publick view; but thoſe things concerning the <hi>Author</hi> and not <hi>me,</hi> who have a ſtock only going in the publick Company, and am no private Trader; I paſs thoſe conſiderations over, ſeeing good things (as the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> long ſince obſerved) the more common, the better they are. And he that cannot ſpeak within doors, may ſometimes take liberty to ſpeak without doors, eſpecially when thoſe within doors ſeem to forget the moſt material points. Something I would alſo ſay of the Diſcourſe it ſelf; but becauſe it is a Proverb as old as <hi>Apelles</hi> himſelf its Author, <hi>That the Shoemaker muſt not go above his Laſt:</hi> I will pray in aid of my Lord <hi>Bacon,</hi> and deſire him to be of Counſel for me. And firſt, for the <hi>method and manner</hi> of handling, thus he ſpeaks,<note place="margin">Advan. of L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ing.</note> 
               <hi>The form of writing which beſt agrees with ſo variable and univerſal an argument</hi> (as is the handling of Negotiations and ſcatter'd Occaſions) <hi>that would be of all other the fitteſt which</hi> Machiavil <hi>made choice of, for the handling of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs of Policy and Government; namely, by Obſervations and Diſcourſes, as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erm them; upon Hiſtory and Examples.</hi> For knowledge drawn freshly, and, as it were in our view, out of Particulars, knows the way beſt to Particulars again; and it hath much the greater life for Pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe, when the Diſcourſe or Diſceptation attends upon the Example, than when the Example attends upon the Diſceptation: for here not only order but ſubſtance is reſpected. And as to the <hi>matter,</hi> who would not but be in a paſſion, to ſee the world undone by inſufficient Counſellors? or, to ſpeak in our own Dialect, ſo many good Ships loſt, as it were, in the very mouth of the Haven, through unskilful Pilots? And to ſee fighting Armies neglected, and impertinent things relied on? Let him therefore ſpeak to theſe two things. To the <hi>firſt.</hi> The ſpeech of <hi>Themiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les,</hi> taken to himſelf, was indeed ſomewhat uncivil and haughty; but if it had been applied to others, and at large, certainly it may ſeem to comprehend in it a wiſe Obſervation and a grave Cenſure, Deſired at a Feaſt to touch a Lute, he ſaid, he could not <hi>Fiddle,</hi> but yet he could make <hi>a ſmall Town a great City</hi> Theſe words drawn to a politick ſenſe do excellently expreſs and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguish two differing abilities, in thoſe that deal in buſineſs of Eſtate. For if a true Survey be taken of all Counſellors and States-men that ever were, and others promoted to publick charge, there will be found (though very rarely) thoſe which can make a <hi>ſmall State great,</hi> and yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>Fiddle:</hi> as on the other ſide there will be found a great many, that are very cunning upon the <hi>Cittern or Lute,</hi> (that is in <hi>Court-Trifles</hi>) but yet are ſo far from being able to make <hi>a ſmall State Great,</hi> as their gift lies another way, to bring a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and Flourishing Estate to Ruine and Decay.</hi> To the <hi>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nd</hi> thus. Walled Towns, ſtored Arcenals and Armories, goodly races of Horſe, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots of War, Elephants, Ordinance, Artillery, and the like; all this is but a <hi>Sheep</hi> in a <hi>Lions</hi> skin, except the breed and diſpoſition of the People be ſtout and Warlike. Nay number it ſelf in Armies imports not much, where the people is of a faint and weak courage<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For, as <hi>Virgil</hi> ſaith, It never troubles a <hi>Wolf,</hi> how many the <hi>Sheep</hi> are. And a little after, A man may rightly make a judgment, and ſet it down for a ſure and certain truth, that the principal point of all other which reſpects the Greatneſs of any Kingdom or State, is to have a RACE of Military men.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourses">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41638:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>DISCO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RSES,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He great thing which has diſturbed the Peace of Europe, filled it with blood and ſlaughters, and ſhaken the dismembred Kingdoms and States thereof, has been the huge deſigne of the <hi>Univerſal Monarchy;</hi> a deſigne which (by a kind of Faſcination) has poſſeſſed the Genius of the Spanish and French Monarchies, which therefore, in their turns, have been dangerous to all Europe. But the French have made nearer approaches to the Throne of ſuch extended Empire then the Spaniards. Let us then look upon the means and advantages, the moſt Chriſtian King has, to purſue ſo vaſt a deſigne, as if he would plow up the Air) To the end our minds may be ſtirred up, (if any thing will ſtir them: to raiſe up thoſe Banks, which (under that Providence, to which, nothing is ſo high, to be above it; nothing ſo low, to be beneath it; nothing ſo large, but is bounded; nor, nothing ſo confuſed, but is ordered by it.) will circumſcribe ſuch wild and boundleſs ambition, within its own limits.</p>
               <p>And for our incouragment, let us by the way, hear the judgment of that excellent Man, <hi>Sr. Walter Raliegh,</hi> in the caſe of the Spanish Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, which then was, what France now is, to the reſt of Europe. His words are theſe. Since the fall of the Roman Empire (omitting that of the Germains, which had neither greatneſs nor continuance) there hath been no State fearful in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> but that of the <hi>Turk;</hi> nor in the <hi>Weſt</hi> any Prince that hath ſpred his Wings far over his neſt, but the <hi>Spaniard;</hi> who ſince the time that <hi>Ferdinand</hi> expelled the Moores out of Granada, have made many attempts to make themſelves Maſters of all Europe. And it is true, that by the treaſures of both Indies, and by the many Kingdoms which they poſſeſſe in Europe, they are at this day the moſt powerful. But as the Turk is now counterpoiſed by the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian, ſo inſtead of ſo many, millions as have been ſpent by the English, French, and Neatherlands in a defenſive War, and in diverſions againſt,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41638:3"/>them, it is eaſie to demonſtrate, that with the charge of two hundred thowſand pound; continued but for two yeares or three at the moſt, they may not only be perſwaded to live in peace, but all their ſwelling and overflowing ſtreams, may be brought back into their natural Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels and old Banks. But to go on.</p>
               <p>France then is come to the greateſt perfection in reſpect of Domeſtic Empire it is capable of. For 1. whereas heretofore the body of that Kingdom was not intire, but ſubject to ſeveral great Barons, who were able not only to expoſtulate, but to contend with the King, the are all brought now to a dependence on the Crown, and becom moſt obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quious to it. And beſides, many of the richeſt and moſt potent of them are of the blood Royal; ſo that upon the failer of thoſe who are before them, they, or their poſteritie may ſucced to the Crown, which keeps them firm to it. 2. All thoſe mighty members into which that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was formerly divided, are now annexed to the Crown: So that for largeneſs of Territory, and compacted and united ſtrength, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com the moſt formidable Kingdom in all Europe. And as by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of theſe, they have ſecured themſelves againſt all inteſtine Wars, which many times through the intereſts and feuds of thoſe Barons, ſhook the whole Frame of that Kingdom; So, by the latter, they have fenced themſelves againſt all Forreign invaſion. For heretofore all the neighbouring Princes were ready upon every occaſion to invade the Kingdom of France, The Dukes of Burgundy, Britannie, Guienne or Flanders, being alwayes tempting them thereunto, and giving them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, paſſage, and reception. By this means England made two Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts of France, and at other times forced them to buy Peace of them, and pay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> them tribute. But now whoſoever would invade that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, shall not only want theſe for their confederates to invite and aſſiſt them, but shall have them for their enemies. Thus far <hi>Machiavel</hi> has obſerved for ſubſtance. 3. By abrogating the Convention of Eſtates, that King has ſpoyled the people of that power and share in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they have originally had in all the mixt Monarchies of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, and made himſelf abſolute even in the point of raiſing money, which is the blood that fils the veins of that mighty Body. By this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes he has changed the conſtitution of that Kingdom, from mixed to abſolute Monarchy for the kind of it; which is the Form that inables a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41638:3"/>Prince to do moſt miſchief bot at home and abroad. 4. Buth that which is the Crown of this perfection, and may be the ſtrongeſt ſtay of it, is the Naval force now added to the other ſtrengths of that powerful Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, wherein it now equals, if it be not an overballance to, either England or Holland. For this is a maxim; That the power of a Prince whoſe Dominions border on the Sea, cannot be perfect without a force in Shipping able to command the Sea. Wherefore in my opinion (which nevertheleſs is exceeding weak) one of the greateſt miſchiefs this War has produced, is, That it has given occaſion to France to becom mighty in Naval power. And that miſchief can never better be demonſtrated then by this conſideration: That there was never before any example upon Earth of a Triumvirate of mighty Nations in a vicinity of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood one to another, and bordering upon the ſame Seas, equally powerful in Naval ſtrength. The conſequence of which muſt of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in time to com, be, a perpetual emulation and jealouſy, greater, by how much either an Union or diviſion of three is more perfect then of any other number. Whereby it muſt neceſſarily com to paſs, either that ſom two of the three ſhall alternatly, or by turns fight againſt the third; Or that two of the three ſhall agree to extinguish the power of the third, that themſelves may remain in indifferent terms, without jealouſy one of another. It is now long ſince France wanted but one of three things to help them to drive on that huge deſigne of ambition for the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Monarchy, which has ſo long ſwelled their hearts. To bring Holland under a kind of feudal protection of that Crown, by which means they might ſerve themſelves of their Ships and Seamen: Or to make themſelves maſters of the Spanish Netherlands: Or laſtly to grow great in Naval ſtrength at home. For France has been dangerous enough to the reſt of Europe, whilſt they were in a manner without ſhipping: Inſomuch that thoſe two things were obſerved of them in the time of <hi>Queen Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth;</hi> That France could never abſtain from War for above two or three years together; And that they could never be poor. 5. and laſtly, To all theſe may be added the new Conqueſts and acquiſitions of the French. But nevertheles it may be doubted, whether that Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy has received any real acceſſion of ſtrength by thoſe Conqueſts, in caſe it should com to feel the shock of a powerful and vigorous Enemy. It is true indeed (what <hi>Machiavel</hi> has ſaid) That the Conqueſts of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41638:4"/>wealths that are ill Governed, and contrary to the Model of the "Romans, do conduce more to the ruin, then advancement of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. But when we shall a little penetrate (what he elswhere ſayes) That when we have obſerved the Hiſtories of former times, we shall find, that Common-wealths had generally but three wayes of enlarging their Empire. One is that which was obſerved by the <hi>Tuſcans</hi> of old, who entered into a League of Confederacy with ſeveral other Common-wealths, with condition of equality, that no particular should have any degree or authority above the reſt, and that comprehenſion should be leſt for all their new Conqueſts to com in, not much unlike the practice of the <hi>Switzers</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> of late, and the <hi>Achaians</hi> and <hi>Aeto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> of old. Another way of extending your Empire, is, by aſſociating with ſeveral Cities, but ſo, as that the dignitie of the Command, the ſeat of the Empire, and the honour of the enterpriſe may remain with you, which was the way obſerved by the <hi>Romans,</hi> and it was pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to them; no other people has obſerved it, and certainly no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is to be found. The third is the way of the <hi>Spartans,</hi> and <hi>Athenians,</hi> who entertained no Confederates, but whatever Territories they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, they annexed them to their own. Which way is undoubtedly the worſt of the three, as appeared by the two ſaid Republicks, who were ruined upon no other accompt, but becauſe they had graſped more Dominion then they were able to hold. I ſay, theſe things diſtinctly conſidered, and the laſt way being that which the French practice in their Conqueſts, it makes the doubt yet greater.</p>
               <p>From that of the State, if we deſcend to the conſideration of the perſon of the King, it gives us theſe two momentuous Obſervations. 1. It ſhewes us how neceſſary a thing it is for a Prince that would either defend or enlarge his State, to excel in practical Wiſdom, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in application, conduct and purſuit. For by that meanes he shall alwayes be ſerved of wiſe and excellent men. For it ever was, and ever will be true; as the Prince himſelf is, ſo are his Counſel, and thoſe that are about him. A weak Prince will never endure wiſe men; nor can wiſe men ever be ſafe under an inadvertent Prince. And it gives him mighty advantages over the Princes and States that are about him; eſpecially if their adminiſtrations be ſlow, weak, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs. And it is commonly ſeen when a great man riſes in the World,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41638:4"/>either that he is alone, or that the magnificence of his actions ſwallow up the weaker efforts of others, as the Sea does the Rivers. And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That when a wiſe and Martial Prince riſes, and is ſucceeded by one or two Princes of equal condition to himſelf, without a puſillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous interpoſed, they may do very great things in the world; ſince the ſucceſſion of two ſuch Princes alone, <hi>Philip,</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Macedon</hi> was ſufficient to Conquer the World. I conclude therefore, That if the preſent King of <hi>France</hi> ſhould be ſucceeded by a Prince of equal Vertue to himſelf, they would ſwallow up the greateſt part of Europe. But becauſe the great things of a Monarchy begin and end with one or a few Princes; and it is rarely ſeen, that three ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Princes immediately ſucceed one another, without ſome effeminate or ill-conſulted Prince between, I am of opinion, that Monarchy will ſink with its own weight.</p>
               <p>Now having taken a view of the force and ſtrength of this Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and the ſufficiency of her preſent King, let us next conſider what their next attempts are like to be. In general they will do theſe two things, What they begun by War, they will purſue in Peace: for they had no other deſign in making Peace, than to diſarm their Enemies, break their Confederation, and hinder <hi>England,</hi> from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into it, that they might inſult over the world, by a Peace more ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical than the War of a Gallant Enemy. And then when the injur'd World can bear their inſolencies no longer, out of the elements of this Peace they will raiſe up a new War. For that Prince that would make great Conqueſts, muſt make ſhort Wars, and renew them often. <hi>Holland</hi> they will not attaqne, at leaſt not this year, for two important reaſons. Becauſe <hi>Flanders</hi> lies between that and <hi>France.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, they will go as ſoftly as they can, till towards the latter end of the Summer, for fear of awaking them out of that ſleep, their waſted Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and trading Humour have caſt them into. And <hi>England</hi> their ſtomacks do not ſerve them to meddle with. For though it be true that whoſoever he be, that ſhall attempt to ſet up an Univerſal Monarchy in Europe, will firſt or laſt find <hi>England</hi> the ſtrongeſt bar in the way; I ſay <hi>England,</hi> which is not only the ſtrongeſt, but now the only ſtrong Kingdom that is in Europe, next to <hi>France.</hi> And therefore <hi>Philip</hi> II. of <hi>Spain,</hi> after al his vain attempts and purſuit, turned himſelf upon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41638:5"/>
                  <hi>England;</hi> in which though he miſcarried, yet he maintained a long War in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Yet the French will think to ſerve themſelves of the ſupine negligence of <hi>England,</hi> and ſtill hope that they may have Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations therefor their mony, till they have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> up the reſt of Europe, as they eat bread. And beſides, they wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a better way to diſtreſs <hi>England,</hi> and more effectual than by any point blanck attaque which they can make upon it, as we ſhall ſee anon: Laſtly, there is yet one very important reaſon, and that is, they are afraid of <hi>England;</hi> and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if God had not placed in man the iraſcible affection of fear, he would be much a wilder creature than he is. But leſt the truth of this ſhould be doubted; it will not be amiſs to call a Foreign Witneſs, and that is <hi>Machiavel,</hi> whoſe own words are; <q rend="margQuotes">The French are in great fear of the Engliſh, for the great inroads and devaſtations which they have made anciently in that Kingdom; inſomuch that among the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people the name of Engliſh is terrible to this day: But he adds, There was not then the ſame reaſon for it.</q> it is true, there are not ſo ſtrong reaſons why they ſhould fear us ſo much now, as they did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, our advantages which we had over that Kingdom being moſt of them ſoft, and that Monarchy come to its full ſtrength, and the greateſt perfection it is ever like to ſee. And yet there be very ſtrong reaſons why they ſhould yet fear us, and if they do not apprehend them, it is no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies fault but our own. And I ſay, that both the Spanish and French Monarchies inherit ſuch a remembrance of the Engliſh as the Romans did of <hi>Hannibal.</hi> Nay, I think it may be truly affirmed, That <hi>France</hi> is more afraid of the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (that is, the King and the Eſtates of Parliament, for they are all comprehended under the word Parliament) than of any one, if not of all the Princes and States of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</p>
               <p>But if <hi>France</hi> will do neither of theſe, what is it then that they will do? I anſwer, We muſt not take our meaſures by thoſe reports they cauſe to be given out up and down the world, to caſt a miſt before the eyes of their Neighbour-Princes and States as Jugglers do; nor when they ſeem to look far abroad muſt we regard it; but conſider by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Rules of Prudence, what is ſit for them to do, and what we our ſelves would do, were we in their caſe. I ſay then, that the greateſt and wiſeſt thing which <hi>France</hi> can do next, is to make himſelf maſter of the reſidue
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41638:5"/>of the Spanish Netherlands, and particularly to ſeize upon Oſtend and Newport. And when he has don that, to turn his whole force upon the Empire, not omitting in the meane time to attempt all that he can do there, as well to amuze and divert them, as to open his way to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Conqueſt of that branch of the miſerable houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To demonſtrate this, I know no better way, then a little to conſider, and diſcourſe upon the conſequences of this, with reſpect unto <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland.</hi> For <hi>England.</hi> If the French be permitted to become ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Spaniſh Netherlands, and to poſſeſs <hi>Oſtend</hi> and <hi>Niewport,</hi> then <hi>England</hi> will not only not have a footing on the Main, but all the Sea-coaſt oppoſite to the whole body of it will be in the hands of the French, always Enemies to <hi>England</hi> in Intereſt and Humour. And if he pleaſes to look over the Sea, he may ſeize upon <hi>Ireland</hi> when he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which will always lie open to him, and where he will find Papiſts enough to entertain and joyn with him. And let it be remembred, that <hi>Ireland</hi> is in a manner already cut off from <hi>England</hi> by the Iriſh Act. And what would <hi>England</hi> then be, but an Iſland hemm'd in by the Sea, and their Enemy its maſter, and ſhut out of the world? By this means they will be precluded from ſending any ſuccours to the reſcue or relief of thoſe Provinces. And by this means alſo it muſt neceſſarily come to paſs (which is worſt of all) that <hi>England</hi> muſt loſe both the Dominion of the Sea, and their Trade; and in time will not be able either to build or ſail Ships out of their own Ports, without the Licenſe of <hi>France,</hi> And ſo will be in a fair way to become a Feudal Province of <hi>France.</hi> And thus we ſee <hi>England</hi> may be diſtreſſed without warring directly upon it. It is the greateſt blemiſh in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, (celebrated in our Hiſtories for one of the wiſeſt of all our Princes) that he ſuffered <hi>Britany</hi> to be loſt, and annexed to the Crown of <hi>France;</hi> a ſoul ſpot in ſo beautiful a Picture, as he is taken by the Pencil of my Lord <hi>Bacon.</hi> And the more I think of theſe things, the more I am confirmed, that we ſhall ſtir up the juſt indignation of thoſe that are to come after us, againſt our memories; and it will be the wonder of ſucceeding Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that ſo great a King as the King of <hi>England; in a War that had for its ends an Univerſal Monarchy for the moſt Chriſtian King, and the ſubverſion of the Proteſtant Religion and Intereſt;</hi> The one as fooliſh and impoſſible to be effected, as the other is full of monſtrous and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41638:6"/>impiety towards God, And to which ends our Enemies have been travelling through a Sea of Blood, and all thoſe crooked ways the firſt attempter againſt God, beat out to thoſe that travel with Pride, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and Impiety: I ſay, that ſuch a King, in ſuch a War, and ſuch a Peace as followed it, ſhould ſit ſtill, and ſuffer himſelf to be (as it were) beſieged in his own Kingdom, whilſt he ſuffered <hi>France,</hi> not only to grow to an over-ballance to <hi>England</hi> in Naval force, but to plant himſelf all along on the oppoſite ſhore of the main Continent, and in the mean time to ſuffer the greateſt part of <hi>Europe</hi> to be conſumed with the flames of an unjuſt War, and be ſacrificed to the ambition of <hi>France.</hi> An ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation greater, by how much <hi>England</hi> has been famous for holding and caſting the Ballance of Europe, and protection of the Proteſtant Religion. Since therefore it is a royal vertue in Kings, not only to avoid Flatterrers as a Peſt, but to encourage ſome body to tell them the truth roundly, ſtill preſerving the dignity of their perſons, and the majeſty of their ſtate; I think a man cannot do better than to bring things home to them: for if Princes would but a little reflect, and look back upon the times paſt, where they might ſee the beauty that is upon the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of good Princes, and the deformity of that of the bad, they would ſee the excellency of plain dealing, and the odiouſneſs of pernicious flattery.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Holland.</hi> It will be enough to ſay, That if they ſuffer the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Netherlands</hi> to be loſt, <hi>France</hi> will not only claim, by a Title prior to theirs, all the Conqueſts and Dominions of this State in <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Brabant,</hi> but may ſet up the Title of the Houſe of <hi>Burgundy</hi> to the whole Seventeen Provinces: and finally, that they will have a very bad Neighbour.</p>
               <p>I conclude therefore, That it is the intereſt of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> by all means, not only to preſerve the reſt of the <hi>Spanish Netherlands</hi> from falling into the hands of <hi>France,</hi> but to make him vomit up what he has already ſwallowed of them. For beſides what I have already ſaid, If <hi>France</hi> once becomes maſter of thoſe Provinces, <hi>Holland</hi> and the reſt of the Provinces of the League will become an eaſie and cheap prey to him, which concerns <hi>England</hi> not a little in point of Intereſt. And to keep thoſe Netherlands in the hands of <hi>Spain,</hi> is, (I think) more the advantage of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> than it is of <hi>Spain</hi> it ſelf.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41638:6"/>For of <hi>Spain</hi> we are ſecure, becauſe he is weak, at that diſtance, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will, nor can incroach upon his Neighbours: and ſo we preſerve the greateſt Bank of ſecurity to both, againſt the Inundations of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude this part. For the moſt <hi>Chriſtian King,</hi> we are no doubt to look upon him as the miniſter of Gods indignation, howbeit he mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not ſo, but has done all theſe things in pride and cruelty, and attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted their ſucceſs to his ſtrength and wiſdom: For the power both of Satan and wicked Kings is from God, but the will and malice is their own. Therefore the French King has made uſe of all theſe powers and advantages to do evil; evil I ſay, than which the moſt mercileſs Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, and deſtroyers of the earth (whom God has ſaid he will deſtroy) have not in any the moſt barbarous age of the world, committed greater, or more crying to the righteous God for vengeance. And a Prince affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with ſo vaſt and wild ambition, is to be looked on as an enemy to mankind, as a proud attempter to deſtroy the bounds which God has ſet. And therefore if ſo excellent hope, that God will ſtop the way againſt our enemies, if we return to him; if the preſervation of the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; the liberties of our Countreys; the great intereſts of mankind; or whatſoever other excellent conſideration we can propoſe to our minds will move us, let us behave our ſelves like men, and do ſome great thing worthy our remembrance.</p>
               <p>And this brings me to the ſecond part of my diſcourſe. In the firſt we have ſeen the miſchiefs, let us now conſider of the remedies.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe there is no ſeparate Kingdom or State in Europe ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ballance the weighty Body of the French Monarchy, nor any of their ſtrengths in disjunction, competent to be oppoſed againſt ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable force; therefore there muſt be a new fond of Power and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt raiſed up, ſufficient to keep the ballance of Europe from being called back into a <hi>Chaos,</hi> out of which the French may form an <hi>Univerſal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> according to the <hi>Idea</hi> they have conceived thereof.</p>
               <p>And this can by no means better be done than by <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> entring into a <hi>new League,</hi> for the mutual and reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procal defence of themſelves, and their Confederates, that ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into ſuch League, and for preſervation and defence of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Netherlands;</hi> and for reſtraining the further growth and increaſe of the <hi>French Monarchy,</hi> and hindering their incroachments upon the reſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41638:7"/>of Europe. The excellency of which <hi>League</hi> will appear by this; That the ends of it are in a manner common to all Europe: For though the preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion be moſt the concernment of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> yet the ſpecial and immediate end of the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and the general end of holding the Ballance of Europe is <hi>Univerſal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon occaſion of the beginning of the War between the Latins and the Romans, <hi>Machiavil</hi> has delivered this Rule; <q rend="margQuotes">That in all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations, it is beſt to come immediately to the point in queſtion, and bring things to a reſult, without too tedious a heſitation and ſuſpence.</q> And the reaſon of this is founded upon divers obſervations which he ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers out of ſeveral parts of the Roman Story: as, <q rend="margQuotes">That weak Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths are generally irreſolute, and ill-adviſed, as taking their meaſures more from neceſſity than election: That 'tis the property of weak States to do every thing amiſs, rnd never to do well but in ſpight of their teeths; for there is no ſuch thing as prudence amongſt them: That weak and irreſolute States, do ſeldom take good Counſels, unleſs they be forced; for their weakneſs ſuffers them not to deliberate, where any thing is doubtful; and if that doubt be not removed by a violent neceſſity, they never come to a reſolution, but are always in ſuſpence: And that it is a fault peculiar to all weak and improvident Princes and Governments to be ſlow and tedious, as well as uncertain in their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, which is as dangerous as the other.</q> With divers more of the like nature. Wherefore thete may ſeem to be but one thing that may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex us, and that is, Whether this courſe may ſort to the nature of the times and our circumſtances? Touching this point the ſame Author gives this Rule, <q>That the occaſion of every mans good or bad fortune con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in his correſpondence &amp; accommodation with the times.</q> The wary courſe that <hi>Fabius</hi> took againſt <hi>Hannibal</hi> was good, becauſe the times and the condition of the Romans ſuited to it: But had the ſame courſe been holden on when <hi>Scipio</hi> undertook the War, <hi>Hannibal</hi> might have ſtaid in <hi>Italy;</hi> but the times being changed, they alſo altered the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of the War. And it is certainly true, That to every purpoſe there is a time and a judgment, therefore the miſery of man is great upon him, becauſe the time is hard to be diſcerned: for, if the time be miſſed, things cannot ſucceed: for man knoweth not his time. If a man chuſes a wrong
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41638:7"/>time, he may labour and travel, not only in vain as to the iſſues deſigned, but may bring forth his own deſtruction; for the univerſal influence and concourſe of the firſt Providence is wanting. But when we ſhall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſider, that there is no other way left; that the French King will neither be quiet himſelf, nor let any body elſe alone; and that we muſt either throw up the Cudgels, and let him domineer as he pleaſes, or do ſomething that may either deter him from attempting further, or if he does, may ſhew him there is as good iron in the world as any he has in <hi>France.</hi> I ſay, things being thus, I can foreſee no objection of weight againſt the propoſition. That State that will defend it ſelf, muſt be in a condition to offend its enemies. And ſo long as this <hi>State</hi> ſhall give oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to <hi>France</hi> to apprehend that they are afraid of him, he will uſe them as Dogs.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſince <hi>this</hi> is like to be a <hi>League</hi> of as great importance as has been made in the world a good while, to render the ſame ſecure to the parties; to add majeſty and grandeur to it; to render it more ſacred; and to give it weight and reputation in the world; it will be neceſſary, that <hi>the ſame</hi> be approved, ratified, and confirmed both by the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of England,</hi> and the <hi>General Estates of the Seven Provinces,</hi> in an extraordinary Aſſembly. I confeſs the thing is both very extraordinary and magnificent, and will make the times famous. But the arguments that inforce the neceſſity thereof are irrefragible; the demonſtration whereof I ſhall leave this whole diſcourſe, and the dignity and weight of the matters themſelves, to give evidence unto: and ſhall ſay no more in this place, Than that there is nothing that Princes and States may more juſtly value themſelves upon, than Faith and Sincerity, in their Leagues, and Treaties, and Negotiations with other Princes and States: and inſincerity or Stare-hypocriſie leſs becomes the majeſty of State, than it does private perſons in moral and civil actions.</p>
               <p>But before we go any further, it will be but neceſſary to anſwer an Objection that may be made on the part of England, and that is, That to confirm a <hi>League</hi> by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> will weaken the <hi>Kings Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi> To which I anſwer 1. <hi>Ad hominem;</hi> That which has been don in the time of former Kings, and thoſe the greateſt and wiſeſt of our Princes, and did not leſſen their <hi>Prerogative;</hi> may be don again without weakening the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of the preſent King. But this thing has been
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41638:8"/>often don in former Parliaments, as our Rolles of Parliament, Records, Law Books and Hiſtories shew. But I shall content my ſelf to name two or three of the moſt Principal, as ſufficient.</p>
               <p>A League and Alliance was made between King <hi>Henry</hi> 5. his Heires and Succeſſors, and <hi>Sigiſmond King of the Romans</hi> his Heires and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors Kings of the Romans, and was confirmed by Act of Parliament. <hi>Coke Inſt, pars</hi> 4.156. <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi> 4. <hi>H.</hi> 5. <hi>N<hi rend="sup">o.</hi>
                  </hi> 14.</p>
               <p>That illuſtrious Peace, 9. <hi>H.</hi> 5. made between <hi>Charles</hi> the 6. of France, and the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> 5. of England (who was the very <hi>Alexander</hi> of the Kings of England for magnificence) by which the King of England had confirmed to him the Regency of the Kingdom of France during the life of <hi>Charles,</hi> and the ſucceſſion of the Crown after his death, was ratified by the three Eſtates of France, and ſworn to by the <hi>King of England in Parliament,</hi> and by the <hi>ſame Parliament</hi> ratified.</p>
               <p>And 11. <hi>Henry</hi> 7. the ſame caſe happened again. The three States of the Kingdom joyned with the King in the ratification of a Peace with France in the ſame manner. This King was a Prince of great wiſdom and ſufficiency (as I ſaid before); He invaded France with a Royal Army, made them buy a Peace of him, and pay him <hi>Tribute,</hi> which continued yet in the times of <hi>Henry</hi> 8. his Son; nevertheleſs he ratified a Peace by the <hi>Parliament.</hi> So you ſee <hi>two Kings,</hi> one the greateſt Conqueror, as the other was the greateſt Polititian of the Kings of England, <hi>ratifying their Leagues</hi> (which nevertheleſs they purchaſed with their own ſwords) <hi>by Parliaments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo ſacred were our Leagues and Truces held to be in thoſe times, that 2. H. 5. c. 6. It was enacted by Parliament, <hi>That the breaking of Truces should be High Treaſon in the ſubjects of England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But 2. I anſwer <hi>ad Rem;</hi> It is ſaid the Kings Prerogative is to make War and Peace. If the King then make a League, and the Parliament confirm that League, it is ſo far from leſſening that it confirms that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
               <p>That there muſt be a <hi>New League,</hi> and that it muſt have not only more, but larger dimenſions, then the preſent League in being, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: Becauſe the Houſe of Commons in the late long Parliament voted, <hi>That the League offenſive and defenſive, between his Majeſtie and this State, is not according to their Advices given to his Majeſtie,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41638:8"/>nor purſuant to the ends by them propoſed.</hi> Which vote has blaſted the preſent League: And if you should call twenty Parliaments, they would all be of the ſame opinion.</p>
               <p>And becauſe all humane Providence is short-ſighted, there may be a proviſional clauſe added; That where the ordinary proviſions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies of this League shall fall short or diſproportionate, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment shall be called to deliberate of ſupplemental complements of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, that may be adequate to the force that shall attacq the League; which will yet add both ſtrength and reputation to it.</p>
               <p>But not to enter into Common-place diſcourſes, I will inſiſt upon but one thing more in this place, and it is this: There is a Rule which <hi>Machiavel</hi> has obſerved, That the beſt and moſt ſecure way to repreſs the inſolence of an ambitious and powerful State, is to preclude and ſtop up thoſe wayes by which he would come to his greatneſs: and that there is not a better or more ſecure way to ſuppreſs the inſolence, or <hi>croſs-bite</hi> the deſignes of ſuch, then to take the ſame ways to prevent, which he takes to advance them. Now then, I think it would be of great advantage to this League (as every body may eaſily apprehend) to put <hi>Oſtend and Neuport</hi> into the hands of <hi>England.</hi> And if <hi>Spain</hi> will ſuffer themſelves to hear reaſon, and be perſuaded to do it, I am without all doubts, a way may be found how they may do it with infallible ſecurity to themſelves, of having the ſaid places reſtored to them, ſo that their end may be obtained, and their hazard prevented.</p>
               <p>Having now ſpoken to that part of the <hi>Parliaments confirmation,</hi> I shall diſcourſe, and that very briefly, the other part of the ratification by the <hi>General Eſtates;</hi> and the more willingly, becauſe I think it may import this State in a double reſpect. And I have conceived it thus. The preſcien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, predetermination and concourſe of God, none denies, tho all have not conceived of them in the ſame <hi>modus.</hi> But the Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian has ſaid, That 'tis a certain truth, that the things of this world are determined, and a ſet time appointed for their duration; but thoſe run throw the whole courſe which is aſſigned them by their Stars, who keep their body in ſuch Order, that it may not alter at all, or if it does, it is for the better. And the way to preſerve ſuch Bodies (<hi>mixt bodies,</hi> he ſpeaks of, <hi>as Common-wealths</hi>) is renovation: for no mere bodies are of long duration, unleſs they be often renewed; and the way be renew
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41638:9"/>them is to reduce them to their firſt principles; and they are reduced partly by external accident, and partly by internal prudence. Thoſe alterations are therefore ſalutiferous, which reduce them towards their principles. But my deſigne is not to enter into the common-place of renovation, <hi>therefore I go on.</hi> And ſince it is in the nature of all things to decline, and tend to depravation; It is the wiſdom of Governments to look often back to their firſt conſtitutions, which are the very <hi>Formalis Ratio,</hi> and Fundamental Laws of their Governments. Therefore let the General Eſtates of the ſeaven Provinces be ſummoned to meet in the great <hi>Zael</hi> in the <hi>Hage,</hi> to theſe two general ends. 1. To renew their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-League among themſelves, which will have theſe two admirable effects: Firſt to cure their internal diſeaſe, and eſpecially that kind of Politic <hi>Paralyſis</hi> of the two Provinces of <hi>Groeningen</hi> and <hi>Frieſland,</hi> which tends to mutulation. Secondly to reſtore a kind of new life and vigour to their Government. No Government can live, that has not extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary remedies to have recource to in extraordinary caſes: <hi>Rome</hi> had its <hi>Dictators,</hi> which kept it in health; and <hi>England</hi> has its <hi>Parliament,</hi> without which its Government could not ſtand. For this cauſe has our Parliaments ſo often renewed our <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> neare <hi>forty times.</hi> And 2. to ratifie this <hi>League</hi> with <hi>England:</hi> For as the firſt defends them againſt internal diſeaſes; So this againſt external Force; the two diſcaſes of which all Governments die. And this will alſo give reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion abroad to the States thus recreated and fenced. And if there be any other Argument neceſſary to inforce the propoſition, it may be drawn from the nature of the Government it ſelf. There are in Story and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiks, but three Diviſions of Common-wealths. Firſt, They are either <hi>Single,</hi> as <hi>Athens, Lacedemons,</hi> &amp;c. Or by <hi>Leagues,</hi> as the <hi>Achaians, Aetolians, Switz,</hi> and <hi>the States.</hi> Secondly they are divided, into ſuch as are for preſervation, as <hi>Lacedemon and Venice;</hi> or for encreaſe, as <hi>Athens and Rome.</hi> Or thirdly, Into <hi>Equal</hi> and <hi>unequal in Libration.</hi> This is a a Government of a League, and for preſervation only, and very unequal; which whoſoever shall thorowly penetrate, shall find cauſe to apprehend the weight of this propoſition: for ſuch another War would shake the States in pieces. And there are but one of three wayes for them; War; Submiſſion to France; or a League with England.</p>
               <p>And if there were time, I think a man should not feare to want either
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41638:9"/>matter or words, to ſet home the Argument. They are now but newly delivered from the moſt dangerous <hi>Criſis</hi> that ever their State paſſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſince its firſt formation; wherein they have laboured under, not only very dangerous domeſtic Convulſions, but the powerful aſſaults of Forreign force. And therefore what Phiſitian that is not a Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bank, would not preſcribe ſome potent reſtorative in ſuch caſe?</p>
               <p>I have now but two things to do, to finish this ſecond part of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours. The one is to ſet down ſome the juſt praiſes of the English Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the end theſe people may be moved to rely upon their friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with the greater confidence. And I would have don it elabouratly, but that my diſcourſe has already drawn it ſelf out to ſo great a length. The other is, The admirable effect that will be produced by opoſeing the <hi>English courage</hi> to the <hi>French fierceneſs.</hi> Let us then but run them over.</p>
               <p>The English have alwayes been ſincere in their Leagues, Alliances, and Treaties. I know preſently what will be caſt in our teeth, and that is the infamous breach of the <hi>Triple League.</hi> But as he shall alwayes be very far from making a true judgment, that shall determin upon one or a few ſingle actions; ſo nothing can be more injurious then to impeach the Faith of a gallant Nation, for that which no body have regreted more then themſelves. The Philoſopher has ſaid, that actions denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate not the ſubject to be ſuch. And it is true in Divinity, That a man is not to be júdged by a few, or many ſingle actions; but by the courſe and tenor of his life. I ſay then, that the excellent virtue of faithfulneſs, has been the general tenor of the English in all times. Let not ſo foul an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignitie therefore be charged on them; but let the crime lye at the doors of thoſe few men who were the Authors and Counſelors of it. And in the mean time I will comfort my ſelf with this hope, that when the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our Parliament shall come to be put upon this League, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie and the whole Nation with him, will be reſtored to the good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of all whoſe intereſt it is not to believe lies. And let me ſay this, that I have not found in Story any nation to be preferr'd to them for the above mentioned excellent qualitie; wherein I may affirm that they have exceeded the <hi>Romans</hi> themſelves: For the Romans paſſionatly affecting an Univerſal Soveraigntie and Dominion, were not ſeldom conſtrained shamefully to prevaricate, to make ſtrained conſtructions
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41638:10"/>of their Leagues, to violate their Faith, and to paſs over all whatſoever reſpects of honour, to travel to the ends of their ambition. Whereas the <hi>English</hi> never can have any intereſt to propogate their <hi>Empire</hi> upon the body of Europe beyond thoſe bounds, which God by nature (his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) preſcribed to them: The moſt they pretend to is, to be <hi>Arbiters</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Princes and States of Europe, as we may ſee in the example of <hi>Henry</hi> 8. who living in an active time, when three ſuch great ſpirited Princes met, as <hi>himſelf, Charles</hi> V. and <hi>Frances</hi> I. of <hi>France,</hi> might have made his own markets; yet ſought no more than to keep the Ballance equal between thoſe two. <hi>England</hi> then, in Peace, has been famous for the excellent vertue of loyalty and faithfulneſs: and in all times for keeping cloſe to that <hi>righteous Maxim</hi> of <hi>holding the Ballance of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope ſteady</hi> a <hi>Maxim</hi> they took up above ſix hundred years ago. In War they have been renowned for their courage, redoubted ſtrength, and great atchievements. In a word, in War they have been juſt, as well as valiant; in Peace kind, and in both ſincere. And for the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the true Religion (without which all other things are either no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or as good as nothing) they have been celebrated above all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Europe. It began there early, and continued in the worſt of times: and ſince the Reformation, her <hi>Divines</hi> has been the moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and pious of the Chriſtian world; as all <hi>Forreign Divines</hi> will be ready to teſtifie. Theſe methinks ſhould be powerful encouragements to this <hi>State</hi> to joyn with <hi>England. England,</hi> in whom the publick ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of true meaning, is inherent: from whom both in Peace and War we may expect not only Juſtice, but even generous goodneſs (to allude to the moſt ancient diſtinction of the Jews:) and who againſt all other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are zealous againſt Popery.</p>
               <p>But that it may appear we do not lay our ſtreſs upon general and rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torical diſcourſes, there are other conſiderations of a more particular na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which muſt not be paſſed over. <hi>England</hi> has been the principal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of ſaving this State twice from deſtruction; once in the Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of their Common-wealth, in the time of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> againſt the <hi>Spaniard;</hi> and now again in the late War, from the <hi>French.</hi> Again, nothing can ſecure this <hi>State</hi> for the future, againſt the miſchiefs impend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>France,</hi> but the friendſhip of <hi>England.</hi> And that <hi>England,</hi> in conjunction with this <hi>State,</hi> is able to ballance the <hi>French Monarchy,</hi> I
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41638:10"/>shall thus demonſtrate. <hi>France</hi> is larger than <hi>England,</hi> but <hi>England</hi> will always afford more <hi>Souldiers</hi> than <hi>France,</hi> I mean <hi>Foot:</hi> and the ſtrength of all Armies conſiſts in the Infantry. The reaſons of this are theſe two. 1. The diviſion of the people. In <hi>France,</hi> and generally in all other Countreys, there are but two diviſions of the people, the <hi>Nobleſs</hi> and the <hi>Peaſants;</hi> but in <hi>England</hi> we have three. 1. The <hi>Nobleſs,</hi> that is the <hi>Nobility and Gentry,</hi> competent to furnish a ſufficient Cavalry. 2. The <hi>Yeomanry,</hi> or middle ſort of people, which make up the great Body of the Kingdom, and who are ſufficient to furnish the greateſt and ſtrongeſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry of any Kingdom or State in the Chriſtian world. And 3. the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior ſort</hi> or Servants; I mean ſuch as work for day-wages, which are very inconſiderable in number to the Yeomanry. The diviſion of the people is one of the principal foundations of Empire: and the diviſion of the people in <hi>England,</hi> being the beſt and moſt perfect of any other in all Europe, it muſt neceſſarily follow, that <hi>England</hi> is capable to endure ſtronger shocks than any other Kingdom or State, founded upon the ſame ballance of Government, and is the moſt perfect Government of its kind in Europe. 2. In <hi>England,</hi> the People, that is, the inferior Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and Yeomanry are an over-ballance, both to the King, Nobility, and Church, which is a defect in Monarchy, and tends to the generation of a Commonwealth. In <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> the King and the Nobility have deſtroyed the People; but in <hi>England</hi> the King and the People have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the Nobility. I ſay then the ſtrength of the Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is in the inferior Gentry and Yeomanry, and theſe exceeding all other Kingdoms in number, ſtrength, and courage, it muſt needs follow if the buſineſs should come to be tried, where blows muſt decide, that <hi>England</hi> would be found an over-match even to <hi>France</hi> it ſelf, if Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration be Demonſtration. But the cauſe and occaſion how theſe two things come to be ſo, that is, why the Nobility of <hi>England</hi> are ſo depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the people become ſo formidable; as you may ſee they are, if you look but upon the Houſe of Lords, and the Houſe of Commons, in our preſent Parliaments. I ſay, the cauſe is, thoſe popular Statutes of <hi>Population,</hi> againſt retainers of the Nobility, and for <hi>Alienations</hi> of their Lands, made by <hi>Henry</hi> 7. (the <hi>Romulus</hi> of the English Kings) which shews the unwarineſs of that politick King, who in ſeeking to cure that dangerous flaw in the Government, of the <hi>Nobilities</hi> being an over-match
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41638:11"/>to the <hi>Prince,</hi> made a far greater, of making the <hi>Commons</hi> formidable: for the one ſtrikes only at a <hi>King</hi> they diſlike, the other at the <hi>Throne</hi> it ſelf; although it be true thoſe effects came not to manifeſt themſelves, till above one hundred years after his death. Therefore a wiſe Prince in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he was, but not long-ſighted.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond. The French have beaten and baffled the greateſt part of the Chriſtian world without fighting, and have oppreſſed them at their own charge. But if ever they should come to deal with an Enemy that would force them to fight, they would shew themſelves to be <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> that is, would ſuffer themſelves to be perſwaded to ſubmit to more reaſonable terms.</p>
               <p>If you look upon the carriage of this whole War, you may preſently ſee, that the wiſeſt thing which the French thought they could do, was ever to avoid fighting, ſuppoſing ſurely, that therein they imitated the wiſdom of <hi>Fabius Maximus.</hi> But this is moſt certain (as the diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes upon <hi>Livy</hi> proves) That a General who deſires to keep the Field, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not avoid fighting when the Enemy preſſes, and makes it his buſineſs to engage him. For in ſuch caſe there are but one of three ways. The firſt is the way of <hi>Fabius,</hi> of ſtanding upon your guard, and keeping your Army in places of Advantage, and this is laudable and good, when your Army is ſo ſtrong that the Enemy dares not attaque you, as it was in the caſe of <hi>Fabius</hi> and <hi>Hannibal:</hi> for if <hi>Hannibal</hi> had advanced, <hi>Fabius</hi> would have kept his ground and engaged him. The ſecond way to avoid fighting, if your Enemy will needs attaque you, is flying, and fight or fly you muſt. <hi>Philip of Macedon</hi> being invaded by the <hi>Romans,</hi> reſolved not to come to a Battel; and to avoid it, he took the way of <hi>Fabius,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped his Army upon the top of a Mountain, and intrenched himſelf ſo ſtrongly, that he believed the <hi>Romans</hi> durſt not have ventured to come at him. But alas, the <hi>Romans</hi> were another kind of Enemy, they not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adventured, but removed him from his Mountain, and forced him to fly with the greateſt part of his Army; and had it not been for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſableneſs of the Country which hindred the purſuit, the <hi>Macedonians</hi> had all been cut off. The <hi>French</hi> were ſtrongly encamped at St. <hi>Dennis,</hi> and did not at all believe that the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> would attaque them, and yet for all their confidence, they could find no other remedy than to betake themſelves to their heels. And this was the greateſt and moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41638:11"/>action of the whole War. The third way to avoid fighting, is to shut your ſelf up in ſome ſtrong Town, which is the moſt pernicious way of all, as making your ruine inevitable. Therefore (as <hi>Machiavel</hi> ſays) to keep the Field, and avoid fighting, is to be done no way ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely as by keeping fifty miles off, and ſending out ſtore of Spies and Scouts that may give you notice of the Enemies approach, and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to retreat.</p>
               <p>Nor is it neceſſary to do all this, that your Army ſhould be very nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous. The <hi>Romans</hi> and the <hi>Greeks</hi> always carried on their Wars with a few men, depending more upon their great order and the excellence of their Diſcipline, than great numbers; but the Eaſtern and Weſtern Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions did all by their multitudes. <hi>Alexander</hi> conquered the world with 30000. men. <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> was wont to ſay that with 15000. men he would go through the world. And yet <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> fought againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> and beat them in two Battels, and was in the judgment of <hi>Hannibal</hi> himſelf, one of the greateſt Captains of the world. The ordinary <hi>Roman</hi> Army conſiſted of about 24000. men, and if they were at any time overpreſſed with numbers, they exceeded not 50000. with which number at one time they oppoſed 200000. <hi>Gauls,</hi> or, if you will, call them <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are two Nations whoſe genius reſembles that of the ancient <hi>Romans,</hi> the <hi>Germans</hi> and the <hi>English,</hi> who are deſcended from them. But there are theſe two differences between them: The <hi>Germans</hi> you ſhall never bring up to make a point blank attaque in the mouth of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, in ſuch faſhion as the <hi>English;</hi> nor again after a rout ſhall you hardly make them rally, as you may the <hi>English.</hi> From all theſe things I make this concluſion, That if the <hi>French</hi> renew the War again, the beſt way will be to oppoſe them with an Army of <hi>English,</hi> and by all means to force them to fight continually, till the Field be too hot for them, and when they can keep that no longer, their Towns will be of little ſervice to them. The <hi>English</hi> have fought many Battels with the <hi>French,</hi> and always beaten them; and yet the <hi>French</hi> have exceeded them much in numbers: as in the memorable Battel of <hi>Poictiers,</hi> where the <hi>English</hi> were but about 8000. and the <hi>French</hi> were 60000.</p>
               <p>And thus I come to the third and laſt part of my Diſcourſe, the office whereof is to diſpoſe into method, ſuch arguments as will be neceſſary to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41638:12"/>be uſed to the ſeveral parties, that is to ſay, the <hi>King, Parliament,</hi> and <hi>this State,</hi> to draw them on to ſuch a <hi>League:</hi> and they are as followeth.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To the King.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. It will ſerve to conciliate, and beget a better underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and the Parliament, and to remove ſome part of that jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie which the people travail with of the Kings adminiſtration, and which will never leave burning till it burn to the Foundations of the Throne if not preuented. And if it attains not the end of introducing other co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operative acts of concord, it will at leaſt avert the haſtening on of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er evils. There be ſome of thoſe things which the Parliament would have, which the King would conſent to, upon condition he might not be preſſed in the reſt, as the caſe of the <hi>Duke of York,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore let them begin with ſome popular great thing that may involve the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts and affections of all.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As to that point of the confirmation by the Parliament, I have ſhewed the preſidents of former times.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Ratifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation here by the General Eſtates will be equipolent to the Ratification in <hi>England</hi> by the Parliament, which ſaves the Kings honour. For thus the parties rather conſpire in one, how to render this League illuſtrious and great, than on their reſpective parts to be forced to any thing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To the Parliament.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Let it move from themſelves, that is, let ſome of thoſe in the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> who are of unqueſtionable reputation for Wiſdom, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and Integrity, be engaged; let them engage others; and let them communicate their Counſels with my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> and that <hi>Party</hi> in the Houſe of <hi>Lords.</hi> Then let the Scheme and Project be propoſed in the Houſe of Commons, then the <hi>Commons</hi> ſeek the <hi>Lords</hi> concurrence; and then let it be offered to the <hi>King,</hi> as the advice of the whole <hi>Kingdom;</hi> for every man is there in perſon, or by repreſentation.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:41638:12"/>
                  <p n="2">2. This will ſhut up thoſe <hi>avenues,</hi> thoſe back doors, by which the <hi>French</hi> have had acceſſes to our Councils, and have influenced them. And conſequently will render the ſitting of Parliaments more calm and ſecure, when that mighty trade of theirs, of <hi>buying Prorogations</hi> ſhall be ſpoil'd, and their <hi>Factors</hi> rendred leſs malignant.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This is an infallible argument, As the end of a thing is, ſo is the thing. The two general ends of this <hi>League</hi> are; To preſerve the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion; and to preſerve and reſtore the Ballance of Europe, by leſſening the power of <hi>France.</hi> And thoſe are the two greateſt ends in Chriſtendom; therefore that thing that has thoſe for its ends is the greateſt thing: and the minds of gallant men are exceedingly moved with great things, and ſtrongly carried to the purſuit of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To this State.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The firſt argument is prudential. Prudence is that vertue, by which, when ſeveral things are offered, we are directed which to chuſe, and which to refuſe; what to do, and what not to do. <hi>Holland</hi> then muſt eiaher make a League with <hi>France,</hi> or with <hi>England,</hi> or remain Neuter.</p>
                  <p>To make a League with <hi>France</hi> is utterly imprudent, for theſe two reaſons.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe <hi>France</hi> aiming at and deſigning an <hi>Univerſal Monarchy,</hi> would only ſecure himſelf of them, till their own turn come, that is, till he hath ſwallowed up the <hi>Spanish Netherlands and Germany,</hi> when he would turn his Force upon them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By ſuch means they would loſe the beſt and ſureſt friend they have had from their Foundation of their State, and that is <hi>England.</hi> And where a <hi>State</hi> is not ſufficient by its own proper force, in reſpect of the weakneſs of the ſame, or the mightineſs of its Neighbours, to defend it ſelf, it muſt of neceſſity rely ſome where els for protection.</p>
                  <p>To remain in a <hi>neutral</hi> condition cannot be. For ſo, inſtead of making one friend, they would make three enemies. And in caſe France should renew the war upon them, England would be won, upon ſuch terms as France would offer, either to join with them, or to ſtand ſtill, and ſee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41638:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Holland ruined. Beſides how impolitic a thing <hi>neutrality</hi> is, any man may ſee that will conſider the obſervations made there on. <hi>Mach. Prince</hi> cap. 21.</p>
                  <p>It remains then, and I know nothing els that remains, <hi>To make a League with England.</hi> For that will have one of two effects. Either <hi>France</hi> will be wholly deterred from attempting upon their <hi>State;</hi> or if he does they will be able with the aſſiſtance of <hi>England</hi> to defend themſelves. This is the firſt <hi>Argument.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The authority and reputation of the <hi>Propoſers;</hi> It is a <hi>League</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the <hi>Parliament of England,</hi> to be entred into with the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom of England.</hi> The Parliament repreſents the whole people of <hi>England,</hi> and commands both the parts and perſons of a great, rich and valiant nation, from whom neither money nor ſouldiers will be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to beat down the power of that proud &amp; inſulting nation of <hi>France.</hi> But theſe people here are afraid of <hi>France,</hi> why then, let them make a league with thoſe of whom France it ſelf is afraid. And withal let them remember this League is to be made with a People, from whom they have received the greateſt benefits, as I have shewed before. And this argument alone will beat down the moſt, if not all the objections that would ariſe againſt ſuch a League, propoſed in any other manner.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The great reputation and ſecurity ſuch a League will give to this State, which will cover them as with wings of Protection againſt <hi>France,</hi> and whoſoever elſe would prey upon them.</p>
                  <p>If I have not expreſſed theſe things ſo as I would, I have done it ſo well as I can in a short time. And ſo ſubmitting it with all decent humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to the grave Conſiderations of thoſe excellent perſonages whom it may moſt concern, I leave it to its <hi>Fate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:41638:13"/>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Hague.</hi> 
                  <date>May 24. 80.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
